Guide to the Cornwall Minister Collection 1796-1943 MS 020 MS 020 MS 020
Cornwall Historical Society
Cornwall Minister Collection
1796-1943
Cornwall Historical Society
Starr, Edward C. (Edward Comfort), 1844-1941
MS 020
1.5 linear feet (3 boxes)
This collection reflects Cornwall historian E.C. Starr’s personal interest in theological matters and Protestant clergyman.
Provenance
These documents were collected entirely by Starr, with the exception of Mrs. Emily Foley Foster’s obituary, which was added to the collection following his death, likely by Emily E. Marsh.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
This collection reflects Cornwall historian E.C. Starr’s personal interest in theological matters and Protestant clergyman. Starr was himself a Congregationalist minister, and during his lifetime he gathered items related to other local preachers. Some of the men found in this collection were Cornwall-area natives, while others worked in Cornwall, or traveled to Cornwall for recreation.
Scope and Content Note
This collection includes materials about Cornwall Minister from 1796-1943.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically by subject/author heading then chronologically within each subject/author heading.
The files are grouped into 2 series:
Ministers
Miscellaneous Materials
Clergy; Religion; Cornwall (Conn.)--history.; Cornwall (Conn.); Correspondence; Pamphlets; obituaries; Starr, Edward C. (Edward Comfort), 1844-1941
- Ministers
  - Francis Barnett
    - Newspaper clipping about Canaan native, Rev. Barnett, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - F.V. Bartley
    - Personal correspondence with E.C. Starr, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Amos Bassett
    - “Election Sermon", 1807 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Biographical sketch, by E.C. Starr, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Record of his life sent to Mr. Calhoun, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Henry Ward Beecher
    - Letter from Beecher to W.H. Brown, about a marriage appointment, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Jacob Albert Biddle
    - Publications by Biddle, 1913; , undated (Box 1, Folder 9-Jul)
    - Obituary, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - H.H. Birkins
    - Correspondence with E.C. Starr, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Everett Clinchy
    - New York Times article, “A Plea For ‘More Than Tolerance", 1940 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Russell J. Clinchy
    - Newspaper article, “La Follette’s Example", 1925 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Norman Coll
    - Program from Coll’s installation as pastor of North Cornwall Church, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Peter S. Collins
    - Correspondence with E.C. Starr, 1905-1908 (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
    - Article, “Tarriffville Baptist Church Has Roll-Call", 1909 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Autobiographical letter, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Printer portrait, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Jonathan N. Crane
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr, 1904 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Hiram Day
    - Marriage notice for John Welch and Elizabeth Bell, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Photograph, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Family correspondence with E.C. Starr, regarding personal and church history, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 24-29)
  - T.S. Duggan
    - Article, “Growth of the Hartford Diocese", 1912 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Austin C. Dunham
    - Article, “Reminisces of Austin C. Dunham", 1912 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - George W. Eastland
    - Personal correspondence with E.C. Starr, 1903-1904 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Frank Field Ellinwood
    - Publications, 1862-1912 (Box 1, Folder 33-34)
    - Obituary, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - E.B. Elmer
    - Personal correspondence with E.C. Starr, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 36-37)
  - Stephen Fenn
    - Printed funeral address given at Cornwall, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Printed memorial discourse for Reverend Fenn, 1875 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Photograph, undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - William G. Fennell
    - Publications, 1881-1914 (Box 1, Folder 41-57)
    - Personal correspondence with E.C. Starr, 1892-1897 (Box 1, Folder 58-59)
    - Memorials and tributes, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 60-62)
  - William Chester Ferris
    - Publications, 1892-1911 (Box 2, Folder 6-Jan)
    - Personal correspondence with E.C. Starr, 1897; , undated (Box 2, Folder 8-Jul)
    - Program for ordination, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Charles N. Fitch
    - Photograph, 1874 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Publications, 1885-1917; , undated (Box 2, Folder 22-Nov)
    - Personal Correspondence with E.C. Starr, 1892-1918; , undated (Box 2, Folder 23-27)
  - Allyn King Foster
    - Publications, 1897-1909; , undated (Box 2, Folder 28-31)
    - Program for 76th Anniversary of New Haven Baptist Association, autographed by Foster, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr, regarding speaking engagement, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Obituary, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Dissertation of Mrs. A.K. Foster, Emily Howard Foley Foster, “The Language of the Northumbrian Gloss to the Gospel of St. Matthew", 1903 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Obituary of Emily Foley Foster, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - T.S. Frost
    - Letter sent to “Mr. Nickerson” about scholarships, 1885 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr, 1893 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - John Calvin Goddard
    - Obituary, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - E. Edwin Hall
    - Booklet, “The Cross, A Pagan Invention", undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Edgar L. Heermance
    - Publications, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - E.A. Henderson
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Samuel C. Jackson
    - Program from memorial service, 1878 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - William Jackson
    - Personal correspondence with Fanny Greenough, 1896; , undated (Box 2, Folder 44-45)
    - Handwritten sermons, undated (Box 2, Folder 46-48)
    - Discourse delivered at Rev. Jackson’s funeral, 1843 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Collected correspondence of E.C. Starr regarding Jackson’s theology and Cornwall roots, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 50-55)
    - Notes and vital information, undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Lewis Jessup
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr, 1892 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Obituary, 1896 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Horace Judd
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - F.S. Leathers
    - Issues of The Worker featuring articles by Leathers, 1901 (Box 2, Folder 60-63)
    - Newspaper clipping, undated (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - James M. Ludlow
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr, 1896 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Notice for new book, 1896 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Newspaper images, undated (Box 2, Folder 67-68)
    - Newspaper story on publications, undated (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - P.H. Mason
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr, 1888 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - William H. McDougall
    - Ordination service program, 1884 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr, 1897 (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Publications, undated (Box 2, Folder 73-74)
  - O.G. McIntire
    - Personal correspondence with E.C. Starr, 1889-1892 (Box 2, Folder 75-76)
  - Elwell O. Mead
    - Autographed circular letter, 1916 (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - First Congregational Church application card from pastorate of E.O. Mead, undated (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - Henry B. Mead
    - Personal correspondence with E.C. Starr, 1890-1902 (Box 2, Folder 80-81)
  - E.H. Mollineaux
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - Newspaper article regarding Mollineaux eloping with a married woman, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - W.H. Moore
    - Personal correspondence with E.C. Starr, 1892-1894 (Box 2, Folder 84-85)
  - F.A. Munson
    - Personal correspondence with E.C. Starr, undated (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - John Nash
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr, 1902 (Box 2, Folder 87)
  - Julius Nelson
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 88)
  - Solomon Palmer
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr from B.W. Pettibone, 1897 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - C.A. Pickett
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr, 1908 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - John Pierpont
    - Correspondence with E.C. Starr, 1888-1910 (Box 3, Folder 5- Mar)
    - Williamsburg, Mass. Congregational Church directory, 1910 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Historical sketch on various ministers, by Pierpont, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Brief sketch on life and career, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Photograph, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Dwight M. Pratt
    - Publications, 1873-1920; , undated (Box 3, Folder 28-Oct)
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr, 1892 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Obituary and memorial items, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 30-32)
  - John H. Prentice
    - Correspondence with E.C. Starr, 1902-1911 (Box 3, Folder 33-34)
  - Newell Anderson Prince
    - Acceptance letter, joining Cornwall’s First Church, 1872 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Copy of writ of attachment against Prince, 1873 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Letter about Prince sent to E.C. Starr by his widow, 1892 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Publications, 1888-1893 (Box 3, Folder 38-39)
    - Memorial items, 1887; , undated (Box 3, Folder 40-43)
    - Glass photonegative, undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - William Sheldon
    - Copy of The Topeka Daily Capital, edited by Sheldon, 1900 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - John Smalley
    - Election sermon, 1800 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Letter sent from D.N. Camp to E.C. Starr, about Smalley, 1908 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Church anniversary booklet, with portrait of Smalley, 1908 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Ralph Smith
    - Text of sermon preached at Lee, Mass., 1847 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Correspondence with Frederick Kellogg, about accepting First Church pulpit, 1851 (Box 3, Folder 50-51)
    - Semi-Centennial booklet of Torrington Third Church, mentioning Smith, 1882 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Carl Stackman
    - Correspondence with E.C. Starr, 1906-1910 (Box 3, Folder 53-54)
    - Article, “Home Missions and the Mormon Problem", undated (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Alfred E. Stembridge
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr, 1891 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - A.H. Stock
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr, 1903 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - James Taylor
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr, 1890 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - E.M. Vittum
    - Image, undated (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Hercules Weston
    - Note from Dartmouth College, regarding Weston’s background, undated (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Edwin A. White
    - Letter sent to E.C. Starr, 1909 (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Brief biography, undated (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Obituaries and memorials, 1925; , undated (Box 3, Folder 69-71)
  - Charles Wetherby
    - Thanksgving sermon given at North Cornwall, 1850 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Published tracts, 1885-1886 (Box 3, Folder 62-63)
    - Memorial booklet, 1887 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Correspondence between E.C. Starr and Mrs. Charles Wetherby, about her late husband, 1892 (Box 3, Folder 65-66)
  - Samuel J. White
    - Correspondence with E.C. Starr, 1889-1902 (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - Walton, NY newspaper with story on White’s death, 1905 (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 74)
- Miscellaneous Materials
  - “Historical Catalogue of the Theological Institute of Connecticut,” mentioning Reverends Ives, Day, Pratt, and St. John, associated with Cornwall, 1881 (Box 3, Folder 75)